Guide to the Seaman family papers 1974.005
Brooklyn Historical Society
Seaman family papers
1752-1838
Brooklyn Historical Society
Seaman family
1974.005
0.25 Linear Feet in 16 folders in one manuscript box
The Seaman family papers (1752-1838) principally concern merchant John Seaman and Willet Seaman, though several other Seaman family members are also represented. The bulk of the collection consists of deeds and other documents concerning land transactions. Several of these deeds relate to land in North Hempstead, Long Island, acquired to establish a manufactory for woolen goods, circa 1816. Other legal documents related to this business are also in the collection, such as partnership agreements and an insurance policy. An indenture for an apprentice from the Overseers of the Poor of Brooklyn and an enslaved Aferican American's bill of sale for John Seaman's purchase also relate to the manufactory, known as Seaman and Cock (the Cock referring to partners John Cock and Townsend Cock). Other land transactions concern Seaman properties or interests on Long Island, New York City, other New York State counties, and other states. Other documents include John Seaman's will, Seaman's conditions for the eventual manumission of the enslaved person he purchased, and correspondence from Willet Seaman supporting quarantine laws to prevent the spread of yellow fever.
Other Finding Aids
A PDF of the original item level inventory provided by the collection donor is available on-line at Brooklyn Historical Society's catablog, Emma. A copy of the inventory is also kept with the collection.
Arrangement
The collection is organized with deeds and other land documents first, followed by correspondence and other document forms.
The collection is no longer in its original order as presented by the donor to the Long Island Historical Society (now Brooklyn Historical Society). The material was originally presented in two "bundles" with documents numbered from 1 to 43. An inventory supplied by the donor listed the items and their relationship. Likely in the mid 2000s, the documents were re-arranged from their sequential order to the present arrangement. Nonetheless, the original sequential numbers are still noted on the documents themselves, on the folder labels, and in the container list. A copy of the original inventory is with the collection.
Biographical / Historical
There are many branches of the Seaman family on Long Island and in the New York area extending back to the 1600s. One of the principal Seamans in this collection is a John Seaman, but it is not immediately clear which of many John Seamans this is. Other Seamans in the collection also have names in common with other Seamans. The researcher is directed to Brooklyn Historical Society's catalog, Bobcat, to identify genealogical works that might help in this regard. The collection itself was donated by the heirs of Mary Jackson Seaman Albert. According to the note accompanying the collection, Mary Albert was born in Brooklyn on January 8, 1815. She was the daughter of John Seaman and Mary M. Hicks, both of Brooklyn, at least later in their lives. The papers in the collection indicate that John was a merchant in New York City at least until about 1815.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Scope and Contents
The Seaman family papers (1752-1838) principally concern merchant John Seaman and Willet Seaman, though several other Seaman family members are also represented. The bulk of the collection consists of deeds and other documents concerning land transactions. Several of these deeds relate to land in North Hempstead, Long Island, acquired to establish a manufactory for woolen goods, circa 1816. Other legal documents related to this business are also in the collection, such as partnership agreements and an insurance policy. An indenture for an apprentice from the Overseers of the Poor of Brooklyn and an enslaved African American's bill of sale for John Seaman's purchase also relate to the manufactory, known as Seaman and Cock (the Cock referring to partners John Cock and Townsend Cock). Other land transactions concern Seaman properties or interests on Long Island, New York City, other New York State counties, and other states. Other documents include John Seaman's will, Seaman's conditions for the eventual manumission of the enslaved person he purchased, and correspondence from Willet Seaman supporting quarantine laws to prevent the spread of yellow fever.
Related Materials
In addition to several Seaman family books on its library shelves, Brooklyn Historical Society also holds the "Seaman family genealogical notes, circa 1685-1865" (call number 1980.033).
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated to the Long Island Historical Society (now the Brooklyn Historical Society) in September 1930, by Grace Albert on behalf of the heirs of Mary Jackson Seaman Albert.
Real property |z New York (State) |z Long Island; Real property |z New York (State); Correspondence; Deeds; North Hempstead (N.Y.: Town); Commerce; Agreements; Enslaved people -- bills of sale; Wills; Cadastral maps; Indentured servants |z New York (State) |z New York; Indentures; Merchants |z New York (State) |z New York; Merchants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Manuscript maps; Woolen goods industry |z New York (State) |z Long Island; Legal documents; Slavery |z New York (State) |z Long Island; New York (N.Y.) |x Commerce; Genealogy; Long Island (N.Y.); Seaman family
- Item Level Inventory, 7140 (Box 1 (A0004), Folder 1)
  General
  The inventory is the original list of items as received from the donor in 1930. Each item is numbered and that number is noted in pencil on the documents themselves. The documents are now foldered differently than the original order of the numbered inventory, but the numbers are noted on the folder tabs and are included below in the folder titles.
- Deeds: New York City (Items 3-5), 1768, 1784; 7141 (Box 1 (A0004), Folder 2)
- Deeds: Long Island (Items 1-4, 34-37), 1752-1818; 7142 (Box 1 (A0004), Folder 3)
- Deeds: New York - Columbia County (Item 9), 1799; 7143 (Box 1 (A0004), Folder 4)
- Deeds: New York - Greene County (Items 15-18), 1804-1815; 7144 (Box 1 (A0004), Folder 5)
- Deeds: Rensselear County (Item 12), 1798; 7148 (Box 1 (A0004), Folder 6)
- Deeds: Washington County (Items 19-21), 1803-1804; 7149 (Box 1 (A0004), Folder 7)
- Deeds: Connecticut (Items 11, 14), 1802, 1810; 7150 (Box 1 (A0004), Folder 7)
- Deeds: Massachusetts (Items 8, 10), 1791, 1807; 7151 (Box 1 (A0004), Folder 8)
- Survey Map: Pennsylvania (Item 24), circa 1790; 7152 (Box 1 (A0004), Folder 9)
- Deeds: Vermont (Item 13), 1817; 7153 (Box 1 (A0004), Folder 10)
- Correspondence: Willet Seaman (Item 31), 1800; 7154 (Box 1 (A0004), Folder 11)
  The folder includes one letter from Willet Seaman to New York legislator Robert Sands in support of the enactment and enforcement of quarantine laws to prevent contagion from ship-borne yellow fever.
- Correspondence: Seaman Brothers Mercantile Firm (Items 22-23, 25-28), 1810-1821; 7155 (Box 1 (A0004), Folder 12)
  Correspondence to John Seaman from debtors and his agents concerning Seaman's attempts to collect monies due him.
- Business Records (Items 38-39, 42-43), 1816-1818; 7157 (Box 1 (A0004), Folder 13)
  Includes a co-partnership agreement establishing Cocks Byrd and Co., a woolen goods manufactory at Hempstead Harbor in Queens County (now part of Nassau County); two agreements concerning the firm Seaman and Cock (possibly the later name of Cocks Byrd); and an insurance policy from Eagle Fire Company for Seaman and Cock.
- Slave Bill of Sale and Conditional Manumission Agreement (Item 32), 1815; 7156 (Box 1 (A0004), Folder 14)
  The folder includes a bill of sale for Robert, an enslaved African-American. In a separate document, the purchaser, John Seaman of New York, agrees to manumit Robert in eight years, but sets out conditions that Robert must observe or else his term of enslavement will be extended. Robert did not sign the document, but it indicates that he has the original.
- Other Legal Documents (items 29, 30, 33), 1827-1838; 7158 (Box 1 (A0004), Folder 14)
  Includes an indenture by which the Overseers of the Poor of Brooklyn placed an eleven year old boy as an apprentice to John Seaman; a bond between John and Sidney Seaman with Amy Hicks; and John Seaman's will.